RG 003, New London County, County Court Files
Connecticut State Library
Despite the fact that all the records of the New London County Court for the period between February 1775 and June 1781 were destroyed by British troops under Benedict Arnold on September 6, 1781, the Files still contain around 120 cases documenting Connecticut' s Revolutionary War experience, mostly between November 1781 and June 1786. As Connecticut morale declined in the later stages of the war, an increasing number of people were charged with trading with and having illicit intercourse with the enemy on Long Island.126 Some 40 cases concern these subjects.127 The bulk of the other cases dealt with such subjects as privateering, hiring of soldiers to serve in the Connecticut Line, and payment of debts owed to Loyalists who left Boston with the British in 1776. Eight lawsuits had a direct relationship to the British attacks on New London and Groton on September 6, 1781.128 The records for November 1781, for example, contain nine war-related cases concerning privateer prize cargoes, illegal trade with the enemy, the transporting of a man "unfriendly" to the United States to Long Island, an assault on militia guards to rescue an illicit trader, and a theft from the store of Thomas Mumford of Groton on the night of September 6, 1781. In one fascinating case, Richard Douglass v. Dudley Saltonsall, the plaintiff as administrator of the estate of John Brown, sued for £400 damages. Lawyers for the defendant argued that the suit should be dismissed because Brown was a transient person with no estate. Lawyers for Douglass replied that Brown had come to New London in 1778 as a prisoner of war, had taken up residence in the town, sailed with the defendant on the Minerva and earned prize shares worth £340, and was killed at Fort Griswold on September 6, 1781 while defending the liberties of his country. The court found for the plaintiff.129
The American Revolution caused profound economic dislocation in Connecticut. One result was the inability of many farmers to pay the State taxes they owed and the State Treasurer secured writs of execution on livestock to pay the amounts owed, although the towns proved to be reluctant to enforce the law. The county sheriff brought lawsuits against the selectmen of Groton, Lyme, Montville, and Stonington in 1788 and 1789 to collect what was owed. In the first such lawsuit, the sheriff attached 400 head of oxen worth £2,400, but they were not turned over for sale and the sheriff sued the selectmen of Stonington. The court ruled in favor of the plaintiff and directed that the defendants pay £2,391-7 damages and £4-6-6 costs to be paid in a variety of currencies, among them hard money, Civil List orders, Lawrence Certificates of Interest, and Soldier Notes.130
The records hold a small amount of documentation on the Embargo and the War of 1812, two cases related to the first and eleven to the second.131 In March 1808, the plaintiffs secured an embargo bond and coasting license from General Jedidiah Huntington, Collector of the Port of New London, but notwith-standing these legal documents, the defendants seized the sloop in January 1809.132 The first War of 1812 case concerned an assault on a sergeant charged with raising troops "for the defence of the state" and the next to last was an unsuccessful lawsuit brought by a merchant from New York against the British consul in New London. The plaintiff, despite the state of war, had secured a permit from the British minister to the U.S. in July 1812 permitting a voyage to the West Indies, but the British Navy captured the vessel. The court found for the plaintiff and the defendant appealed.133
Files for the New London County Court contain a great deal of documentation on minorities, the downtrodden, and the poor, such groups as African Americans, Native Americans, women, apprentices, and transients.
The records include 286 cases on African Americans and other people of color between 1701 and 1774 and an additional 800 for the years 1781 to 1855.134 Despite the existence of a wonderful reference tool, Black Roots in Southeastern Connecticut," the bulk of these cases have not been previously examined by researchers.135 One hundred and sixty-one separate names are found for the period up to the American Revolution and only 61 (38%) of them are represented in Black Roots. To put the matter somewhat differently, Black Roots cites 40 of the 259 cases in which an African American is identified by name. As with other cases and despite the fact that only a minority of African Americans in Connecticut was free prior to the American Revolution, the most common type of case found is that for debt with a free Negro as the plaintiff or defendant. The second largest number of cases concern disputes over ownership, inheritance, or suits for freedom by persons classified as slaves. In a number of additional cases, African Americans are summoned to testify as witnesses in court cases or are attached as property to ensure that the defendant appears at trial or to pay debts after conviction. Other subjects addressed include arson, breach of covenant for failure to pay wages to free Negroes, fornication, malicious mischief, theft, and trespass. For more information on African Americans, see the finding aid New London Court African Americans and People of Color Collection.
Files contain around 240 cases documenting Native Americans in New London County and environs between 1698 and 1774 and another 100 for the post-Revolutionary War era. One hundred and eighty-two Indians are represented, but only 59 appear in Black Roots, and just 29 cases are listed in that same source for the period up to the American Revolution. Suits for debt make up the largest number of cases, while those concerning Indians in their status as servants comes in second, and land disputes follow. The remainder of cases concerns such subjects as assault, defamation and slander, fornication, lascivious carriage, negligence, profaning the Sabbath, and theft. For additional information on Native Americans in New London County, see the finding aid for New London Court Native Americans Collection.
The role of women before the bar is far more significant than one would believe from reading Cornelia Dayton's prizewinning book on the subject and there is little reason to conclude that they were victims of prejudice by the male dominated judicial system.136 Females were plaintiffs or defendants in only a relatively small minority of cases due to the legal principle of coverture.137 Single women and widows could and did sue and were sued and a small number, like diarist Madame Sarah Knight and entrepreneur Mercy Raymond and such women as Mary Dart, Elizabeth Hallam, Elizabeth Livingston, and Sarah Rogers made frequent court appearances. The records also contain a number of cases in which a husband sues to collect a debt contracted by his wife before the date of their marriage. In November 1741, for example, Benjamin Lothrop of Norwich and his wife Mary, formerly Mary Jones of Colchester, sued William Randall for payment on a debt by note dated Sep. 16, 1740 for £10 damages on the failure of the defendant for value received to deliver ten bushels of Indian corn to Jones.138 Women also frequently appeared as witnesses to debt instruments and testified before the county court.
Mercy Raymond (1663-1741) provides an excellent example of a woman who frequently appeared before the court. Left a widow with seven children on the death of her husband in 1704, Mercy was deeded property by both her father and husband and was a wealthy woman. She never remarried and from 1710 to 1735, she was plaintiff or defendant in some 46 lawsuits, 20 for the period between 1712 and 1726 when she was in partnership with Major John Merritt. The relationship between the two is not known, but in June 1717, Merritt was sued for not living with his wife.139 Additional information about Mercy's life comes from a 1748 deposition that contains the information that she had a slave Busso "who was... Infirm In body... and Not Capable of Doing So much Labour as to Earn his Victuals," and who was characterized as "an ill tempered Surly Sort of fellow." Busso, however, mistreated his mistress and on a least two occasions struck her.140
For researchers interested in crimes against women, the records contain ample documentation.
Table 4. Crimes Against Women, 1781-1855
1781-1789 4 5 0 0 40 7 56
1790-1799 4 8 6 1 25 4 48
1800-1809 9 8 7 1 27 6 58
1810-1819 13 19 1 0 33 5 71
1820-1829 22 12 15 0 28 5 82
1830-1839 40 9 9 5 14 1 78
1840-1849 62 2 8 7 18 1 98
1850-1855 36 5 4 5 6 5 61
Totals 190 68 50 19 191 34 552
A clear trend emerges from these figures. The number of physical assaults against women drastically increases, while the number of lawsuits, mostly civil filings, by women suing for child support undergoes a significant decline. The largest number of criminal assaults represents State prosecutions of husbands for abusing their wives. The same is true for prosecutions of threatening assault or murder. Civil assault cases consist of prosecutions by women against men not their husbands. Breach of promise to marry lawsuits consists exclusively of civil cases.
The records include some 140 cases involving indentures, a subject addressed more frequently in town records. Several kinds of cases are found here. Lawsuits concerning the failure of the master to properly train his apprentice in a lawful calling and those involving runaways represent the most common. In the case of John Borman v. John Gibbins, the defendant was reduced to poverty and his son Luke Gibbins was bound by the selectmen of Preston to Borman. Luke ran away in December 1724 to return to his parents. The jury decided that the youth must be returned to Borman.141 In a February 1725 case, Christopher Darrow v. John Savel, Darrow apprenticed his son Ebenezer to the defendant to learn the trade of joiner. Darrow accused Savel of not providing Ebenezer with clothing as the indenture stipulated, but the lawsuit was withdrawn, probably because the parties came to an out of court settlement.142 On occasion, masters abused their apprentices, as in State of Connecticut v. Joseph Rogers. James Davidson was beaten so severely by Rogers that he sought refuge in the house of a neighbor.143 The last such case was heard in 1849, Isaac S. Geer v. Edwin Kimball and George P.Harvey, in which the plaintiff unsuccessfully sued for $200 for wages owed his apprentice William Briggs.144
For researchers interested in the lot of the poor and transients, the records contain hundreds of cases documenting the fate of the poorest whites. Those unable to pay their debt could be jailed or assigned to the service of any person, often the creditor, who would pay the debt. To cite just one example, Elijah Backus v. Jeremiah Lewis, in a case of debt by book, the defendant confessed judgment for £12-1 debt and £0-10-3 costs. Since he was unable to pay this and another debt, he was assigned to the service of Backus for three years.145 Jacob Johnson of Stonington sent a memorial to the June 1772 court stating that he had been confined to the county jail for several months because he was unable to pay Joseph Denison 2d a debt of £12. He wrote that he was poor and unable to support himself while in prison and that he had offered to go into service to pay the debt, but that Denison had refused to allow him to be released.146
Persons classed as transients, e.g. without a fixed abode, are so identified in court records. One such case was Christopher Smieller v. Edmund Tobin, a transient person residing in New London, in a debt by note for £3-6. The defendant claimed that the note had been obtained under extortion as he was unlawfully arrested and kept prison in jail until he signed the note. The jury agreed and the defendant recovered £2-8-8 in court costs.147 Transients appear frequently as defendants in criminal cases. The State's Attorney filed thirty-seven presentments in June 1854, seven against transients for arson, assault, malicious mischief, theft, and threatening to kill.
Disputing parties over care of the poor and mentally incompetent frequently resorted to the courts. Some 230 suits were brought before the court in the post-Revolutionary period, a much smaller number from the earlier era. In March 1819, for example, the court hear disputes over the support of Mulford Babcock and his family, Groton paupers; Isaac Moody, another Groton pauper; sick and helpless George Southmayd of New London; the care of Ezra Robbins, Jr.; plus a petition by Nathan Rose of Griswold protesting the appointment of an overseer over him and pleading for his "Freedom."148 Trials and Files contain hundred of cases concerning those on the lowest rung of society
Those interested in the growth and development of the legal profession in 18th century Connecticut will likewise find these records extremely useful.149 Lawyers became ever more critical throughout the course of the eighteenth century. Legislation allowing attorneys to represent clients was first passed in May 1708. One begins to see lawyers representing clients by the 1720s and by the end of the fourth decade of the century, lawyers represented clients in virtually all disputed cases.150 Researcher can determine who the most prominent and successful lawyers are, the kinds of cases they pleaded, the nature of their legal arguments, and their success ratio in cases in which they appeared.151 The leading members of the New London County bar in 1740 were John Curtiss, Joseph Fowler, John Lee, and Elisha Paine, all of whom played significant roles in the Great Awakening. Curtiss and Paine became Separatists and ceased the practice of law by 1742. Lee, also King's Attorney for New London County, strongly adhered to the cause of awakened religion, while Fowler played a critical role in a 1740 election plot that saw several supporters of awakened religion achieve prominent office. Joseph Fowler from Lebanon in Windham County was the leading person in the New London County bar during the 1730s and 1740s. He often represented commercial plaintiffs from Boston in debt cases and his clients enjoyed great success before the court. A new generation of lawyers began to make their appearance in the 1740s and 1750s, such persons as George Dorr, Matthew Griswold, William Hillhouse, Benjamin Huntington, Samuel Huntington, Richard Law, Samuel Holden Parsons, and Ambrose Whittelsey. The legal careers of these and a number of other lawyers can be traced through Files well into the 19th century, including such prominent member of the bar as Jeremiah G. Brainard, Lafayette L. Foster, Jirah Isham, James Lanman, Charles J. McCurdy, John T. Wait, and Henry N. Waite
The records contain information on a number of such other subjects as, arson, assumpsit,, covenant broken, desertion, fishing rights, forgery, fraudulent contract, guardians and overseers for the mentally and physically incompetent, lotteries, naturalization and legal treatment of foreigners, perjury, probate, and usury, not to mention the violation of statutes concerning tanning of leather, unlawful obstructions across rivers and streams, unlawful smallpox inoculation, and illegal settlement by non-inhabitants, and isolated cases on horse racing, gambling, and performing trick and in shows. County court records, then, represent a rich source for information on a wide variety of subjects.
Endnotes
6Harvey v. Phelps, NLCC Files, Nov. 1768, Box 148, folder 17. In another example, Coit v. Martin, in order to make certain that the defendant appeared to answer a debt by book for £45, the deputy attached on ton of hay, a hogshead of oats, 2 casks potatoes, and one "Right in a pew in the meeting house in Chelsea Parish." Ibid, Feb. 1774, Box 167, folder 4, no. 81.
7Ibid, July 1753, Box 97, folder 14, no. 6.
8Currency was denominated in pounds, shillings, and pence until the late 1790s. Each unit was separated by a dash, thus, £2-17-5 equals 2 pounds, 17 shillings, and 5 pence. Twenty shillings made up a pound and twelve pence a shilling. Some debts are counted in fractions of pennies, called farthings. Four farthings make one penny. Connecticut depended almost entirely on paper currency, called bills of credit. The colony's original currency, called old tenor, had seriously depreciated by the 1740s, so that it took five to ten pounts of old tenor to be equivalent to one pound of lawful money.
9NLCC Files, Nov. 1758, Box 110, folder 1, no. 27.
10Ibid, Box 269, folder 21, no. 267.
11Samuel Green et al v. Moses Warren, Ibid, Box 270, folder 3. For other cases concerning the New London Masons, see June 1807, Box 272, folder 12, no. 59 and Box 273, folder 10, no. 354.
12Ibid, March 1817, Box 317, folder 9, no. 110; Box 317, folder 16, no. 188.
13Not all bailiff and receiver cases concern trade. In one November 1774 case, Samuel Smith and Isaac Smith v. John Pettet, the Smiths asked for a reasonable account of the time the defendant served as bailiff and receiver for rental of a house, shop and land for a three and one half year period owned by the plaintiffs. The plaintiffs asked for £30 damages. Ibid, Nov. 1774, Box 170, folder 8.
14Ibid, Nov. 1774, Box 169, folder 11. Cases that lack document number are No Docket cases.
15The plaintiff failed to make an appearance when the case was called. Ibid, Feb. 1740, Box 61, folder 6, no. 61.
16Ibid, June 1758, Box 109, folder 2, no. 18.
17Ibid, Nov. 1774, Box 169, folder 10.
18Ibid, June 1769, Box 150, folder 19, no. 82.
19The average number of cases filed 1781-1809 was 10.75 per year and that for 1810-55 was 4.6. The decline really begins with the 1814 court sessions, as those for 1812-13 consisted primarily of incidents that took place before the war.
20John Pintard v. John Brown and Samuel Francis, NLCC Files, Dec. 1789, Box 216, folder 17, no. 254; Asa Lee v. William A. Fanning and James P. Sheffield, Dec. 1820, Box 335, folder 5; Silas Beebe et al v. Charles Fordham, June 1835, Boix 380, folder 17; Robert Furlong, Jr. v. John C. Edwards, Nov. 1836, Box 386, folder 3, no. 42; Joseph Lawrence v. William Mayhew, Feb. 1844, Box 407, folder 11, no. 41; Charles F. Smith v. William McLane, June 1844, Box 408, folder 11, no. 150; William Lyon v. Joseph A. Smith et al, June 1850, Box 422, folder 1, no. 714.
21Ibid, June 1795, Box 233, folder 8, no. 91.
22Silas Beebe et al v. Charles Fordham, Ibid, Box 380, folder 17; Christopher B. Chapell v. George Churchill, Box 380, folder 20; and Charles F. Lester and John P. Huntington v. Union Insurance Company, Box 381, folder 11.
23Nathan Allyn v. John Sterling, June 1810, Ibid, Box 286, folder 4, no. 175; William H. Savage v. Nathan Allyn, Ibid, June 1810, Box 286, folder 4, no. 156.
24Ibid, June 1807, Box 272, folder 8, no. 19.
25The following list represents the dates of the first cases involving the named banks: Union Bank (Nov. 1794), Norwich Bank (Dec. 1799), Washington Bank (Mar. 1802), New London Bank (June 1817), Stonington Bank (Nov. 1823), Thames Bank (March 1827), Whaling Bank (Feb. 1834), Merchants Bank (June 1835), Quinebaug Bank (Feb. 1837), and Jewett City Bank (June 1840).
26Elisha Tracy, Charles Carew, Jeremiah Harris, and Augustus Perkins v. Samuel Woodbridge, President Norwich Marine Insurance Company, NLCC Files, Nov. 1803, Box 262, folder 11, no. 223.
27Norwich Marine Insurance Company v. Christopher Raymond, Ibid, Nov. 1803, Box 262, folder 19.
28Ibid, Nov. 1853, Box 431, folder 16, no. 185.
29The number represents an extremely conservative figure because it does not include lawsuits involving corporations that cannot be positively identified as cotton factories and those in which individuals so associated are plaintiffs or defendants.
30NLCC Files, Ibid, June 1813, Box 298, folder 15, no. 114.
31Ibid, Amos Cobb v. Samuel Slater and John Slater, Ibid, Nov. 1832, Box 370, folder 2. See Illustration 20
32Jacob Avery v. Groton, Ibid, Dec. 1788, Box 210, folder 18, no. 122.
33Seisin is the legal term for possession of a freehold estate. Black's Law Dictionary, Seventh Edition (St. Paul, Minn.: West Group, 1999), 1362.
34Most partition lawsuits between 1745 and 1832 are found in Papers by Subject: Partition of Lands, Box 84, folders 1-4.
35Nathan Howard et al v. James Rogers et al, NLCC Files, Feb. 1742, Box 70, folder 20, no. 219.
36Messuage, a dwelling house, especially one with adjacent outbuildings, gardens, and lands.
37NLCC Files, Feb. 1767, Box 143, folder 2, no. 15.
38Ibid, Feb. 1767, Box 143, folder 9, no. 139
39Ibid, Nov. 1773, Box 166, folder 14.
40William Keeney v. Reuben Moore, Ibid, June 1818, Box 325, folder 10; Richard McCurdy and Elizabeth Stewart v. Samuel Green et al, June 1818, Box 325, folder 12.
41In an example of a trespass for theft, Lemon Prime accused Japhet Morgan of breaking into the house with force and arms and carrying away clothes and household goods worth $35. The defendant was found guilty and assessed $2 damages and costs of suit. Ibid, Mar. 1824, Box 345, folder 12.
42Ibid, Nov. 1732, Box 36, folder 10, no. 263.
43Ibid, June 1732, Box 34, folder 13, no. 6.
44Ibid, Nov. 1733, Box 38, folder 14, no. 258; June 1740, Box 64, folder 14, no. 335.
45Ibid, Nov. 1769, Box 152, folder 12, no. 246.
46Ibid, Nov. 1827, Box 355, folder 15. The plaintiffs lost and appealed to the Superior Court.
47Ibid, June 1740, Box 61, folder 15, no. 41.
48Ibid, Nov. 1755, Box 103, folder 9, no. 131
49Ibid, Nov. 1772, Box 163, folder 9.
50Ibid, Feb. 1764, Box 131, folder 6, no. 172.
51Scire facias is a writ requiring the person against whom it is directed to appear and to show cause why a judgment against a person should not be revived. Black's Law Dictionary, 1347.
52NLCC Files, Nov. 1731, Box 33, folder 12, no. 29
53NLCC Files, Nov. 1731, Box 33, folder 12, no. 29
54Ibid, June 1753, Box 97, folder 4, no. 179.
55Ibid, Feb. 1848, Box 415, folders 9-10, no. 614-18.
56Ibid, Prosper Wetmore v. Lucy Fargo and Edward Wentworth, Feb. 1784, Box 186, folder 2, no. 436.
57Ibid, Nov. 1723, Box 23, folder 20, no. 102
58Ibid, June 1738, Box 53, folder 1, no. 59
59Ibid, Feb. 1765, Box 138, folder 2, no. 182.
60The disposition of the case is unknown because Trials for the period between 1705 and 1710 are no longer extant. Ibid, Nov. 1710, Box 5, folder 7.
61Ibid, June 1738, Box 54, folder 10, no. 491.
62Ibid, Nov. 1764, Box 135, folder 1, no. 407.
63Ibid, Nov. 1771, Box 158, folder 13.
64Ibid, June 1726, box 24, folder 9, no. 251.
65Joseph Page v. Gilbert Fanning, Feb. 1769, Box 150, folder 11.
66Ibid, Nov. 1767, Box 145, folder 12, no. 75.
67Trover and conversion is a common law action for the recovery of damages for the conversion of personal property owned by one person by another. Black's Law Dictionary, 1513.
68Ibid, June 1771, Box 158, folder 4, no. 257.
69Ibid, June 1756, Box 105, folder 10, no. 63; Nov. 1771, Box 158, folder 18, no. 125.
70Ibid, June 1772, Box 160, folder 11, no. 101.
71Ibid, Nov. 1773, Box 166, folder 7.
72The category includes 93 trover and conversion cases and 55 replevin ones.
73Beebe Denison v. Stephen Martin et al, NLCC Files, June 1782, Box 174, folder 3, no. 29; Frederick Denison v. Stephen Martin et al, Ibid, no. 30; Abel Gore v. Stephen Martin et al, Ibid, no. 38.
74Richard Godbeer, "'The Cry of Sodom': Discourse, Intercourse, and Desire in Colonial New England" The William and Mary Quarterly, Third Series (52) 1995: 277-80. In another case not mentioned by Godbeer, Samuell Atwell v. Stephen Gorton, the Baptist minister was convicted of illegally marrying Sarah Atwell and Philip Goss because only justices of the peace or ordained ministers were allowed to perform marriage ceremonies. NLCC Files, June 1727, Box 26, folder 5, no. 231.
75Ibid, Feb. 1773, Box 163, folder 17.